Hello friends, welcome to Market Analyst.
In today's video, we are going to
talk about free look. Free
look is designed for investor protection,
but due to lack of information,
most people are unable to use it.
Friends, you will be surprised to know that
in most cases, free look is not available.
I have seen many times that people
go to the branch to get a free look and
submit their application but they do
not take a receipt. In such a situation, whether you will get a free
look or not
depends on the other person. If he has
processed your application, then the free
look will be available. If he
quietly puts your application aside, then your free look will
gradually expire and after that you
cannot cancel your policy even if you want.
Friends, free look is a game of time, that is, the
day you receive the policy cancellation,
from that day you have 15 days' time. This is a relief for you. To get a
free look,
you get 15 days in offline cases and 30 days in online cases.
You will be surprised to know that sometimes the
investor's negligence delays the time
and sometimes the companies deliberately delay it.
If you want to get your
policy cancelled for free, you should
follow this process seriously.
As I mentioned, you get 15 days from the day you receive the policy bond. So,
read your policy bond as soon as possible. If
you find any discrepancy in it or you feel
that you have been defrauded
by the selling manager or insurance agent,
you have
full right to cancel the policy for free. Using this right,
you can get your policy
cancelled for free.
To get a free look at the policy, you have to submit a written
application to your insurance company
branch and also bring your
KYC with you.
If the insurance company asks for your KYC
documents, you will have to submit proof there. Do not forget to
take a cancellation cheque along with you. Along with
submitting your application, do
not forget to get the application receipt from the insurance company
because you must have a solid document on
which date you made the decision.  You have
submitted your application to the company for a free look.
If you take the receipt, then the company will
not stand behind you. If it is the company's fault, then
if you have the receipt, then you
can fight with the company on the basis of the receipt and you can get your refund,
no one can stop it.
After submitting the application,
you have to wait for three to three days.
Within three to three days, you will receive a confirmation email
or message from the insurance company.
If the company has
accepted the application for free look, then your
money will also be debited. If
you do not receive any call, email, message from the company within three to three days and do
not get any confirmation, then
scan the receipt that you had brought from the insurance company. After scanning, you have to
send it to the Grewal team of the company. You can easily find the
email ID of the Grievance Support Team of any company
on the insurance company website. If
you do
not receive any confirmation from the insurance company within three to three days, then
you can send that receipt.  They will scan it and
send it to your email ID and ask them
when your money will be returned. You will definitely get a reply from here
within three to two days of emailing the company. So,
if you look at the time from the first time you submitted your application in the branch, six to eight days have passed till now
and you have crossed two levels.
Usually, you will not have to worry about this.
Your money will be returned. The normal time for
money to come in free look is 10 to
15 days, that is, 15 days is
considered to be the standard time. If the insurance company has
accepted your application, then
friends, many times the insurance company
considers that we are rejecting your application.
This policy cannot be cancelled in pre-look. In
some reasons, that
company gives it there. So what should you do?
If it is not your fault, then what is the next step?
We will go to IRDA, but
if it is your fault, then there is no use of knowing about the code.
Generally, people go to IRDA after
2 months or 6 months
after two free looks, but there
you make a mistake.  You have to submit your request within 15 days. If
15 days are crossed, then
even IRDA cannot do anything
because this is the rule. So if the company,
i.e. the insurance company, refuses and is
not refunding your money, then you
can go to Idea. So what to do here is to
forward the email that you sent to Grebans support team to
IRDA. The email ID of IRDA is
visible to you on the website above.
Friends, right now there is an Excel format of IRDA in front of you.
You will have to provide whatever information IRDA is asking for in this Excel format.
Because you are making a complaint to IRDA,
you already have all this information
because now you are a policy
holder. So, file this Excel and
send it to IRDA along with
attachments in this mail. You can get this format from
IRDA on their website or by calling their toll
free number. So,
in this format, provide whatever information has been
asked by Idea.
Along with this, you have to
write in detail why you are  You are filing a complaint,
after filing the complaint the maximum chance is that
you will get your refund, if it is not your fault but the
insurance company's fault, then the
insurance company will
definitely return your money accepting its mistake, maximum I have
seen is that by the time you reach here
your loss reduces, friends,
before taking the policy an investor
should know the details of the policy, if you get all the
information before taking the policy
then you will not have to consult for free look,
so by doing this you will save your time and the time of the entire
system i.e. the insurance company and
IIT,
thank you very much to all of you for watching the video, see you
in the next video, thank you